Mss.Rec.22 Mss.Rec.22
American Philosophical Society
Songs and Dances of Great Lakes Indians
1952-1954, 1956
Mss.Rec.22
American Philosophical Society
2.0 Item(s)
A compilation LP record of Native American musical and dance recordings made by Gertrude Prokosch Kurath at numerous locations from 1952 to 1954, published in 1956. Also includes a 20-page booklet with extensive background information, biographical info on the performers, explanations of songs, musical analysis, and sheet music.
1 12" phonograph disc; 1 volume, 20 p.
1 sound disc (45 min.): analog, 33 1/3 rpm, mono; 12 in.
Albert, Whitney
Brown, George W.
Buck, Gordon
Buck, Morris
Buck, Richard
Folkways Records.
Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
Lacasse, Fred
Lewis, Thomas
Link, Sam
Martin, John
Miller, Huron
Shagonaby, Susan
Shalifoe, Thomas
Smoke, Percy
Thomas, Eli
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Gertrude Kurath.
Scope and Contents
The record is divided into four sections: Algonquians, Iroquois Animal and War Dances, Food Spirit Dances, and Future Prospects. The Algonquians section is divided into sections according to the location of the recording: Meskwaki of Tama, Iowa; Ojibwa of Lac du Flambeau, Wisconsin; Ojibwa of Baraga, Michigan; Ottawa of L'Arbre Croche, Michigan; Ottawa of Mikado, Michigan; Ojibwa of Isabella Reservation, Michigan. The remaining recordings feature Onondaga, Cayuga, and Seneca performers.
Related Archival Materials
The original recordings for some of the material compiled on this record are available in the recording collections Songs and Dances of the Rural Ottawa and Chippewa Indians (Mss.Rec.20) and Songs from Lac du Flambeau Reservation, Wisconsin (Mss.Rec.75).
Catholic Church--Hymns; Cayuga dance; Cayuga Indians--Music; Eagle dance; Ethnomusicology; Flute--Performance; Fox dance; Fox Indians--Music; Hymns.; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion; Onondaga dance; Onondaga Indians--Music; Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music; Seneca Indians--Music; Sheet music; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Buffalo Head Dance, 1952; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:47; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Roberts, Wilson
    Scope and Contents note
    From an LP titled "Songs and Dance of Great Lakes Indians," Ethnic Folkways Library, 1956. In section titled "Algonquians." Liner notes contain extensive notes on songs and performers, and musical analysis.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Phonograph record) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Fox dance; Fox Indians--Music; Tama (Iowa)
  - Buffalo Head Dance, 1952; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:37; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Roberts, Wilson
    From an LP titled "Songs and Dance of Great Lakes Indians," Ethnic Folkways Library, 1956. In section titled "Algonquians." Liner notes contain extensive documentation. Liner notes contain extensive notes on songs and performers, and musical analysis.
  - Bear-Claw or Grizzly Bear Dance, 1952; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:58; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Roberts, Wilson
  - Pipe of Peace or Calumet Dance, 1952; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:06; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Roberts, Wilson
    From an LP titled "Songs and Dance of Great Lakes Indians," Ethnic Folkways Library, 1956. Liner notes contain extensive documentation. In section titled "Algonquians." Liner notes contain extensive notes on songs and performers, and musical analysis.
  - Soldier or Victory Round Dance, 1952; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:22; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Roberts, Wilson
  - Love Song for Flute, 1952; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:16; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Roberts, Wilson
    Flute--Performance; Fox Indians--Music; Tama (Iowa)
  - Fish Dance, 1952-08-22; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:36; Brown, George; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lacasse, Fred; Link, Sam; Martin, John
    Lac du Flambeau Reservation (Wis.); Ojibwa dance; Ojibwa Indians--Music
  - Pipe of Peace Dance, 1952-08-22; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:37; Brown, George; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lacasse, Fred; Link, Sam; Martin, John
  - Pipe of Peace Dance, 1952-08-22; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:42; Brown, George; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lacasse, Fred; Link, Sam; Martin, John
  - Powwow or Horse Dance, 1952-08-22; 01-10; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:23; Brown, George; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lacasse, Fred; Link, Sam; Martin, John
  - Fortynine Dance, 1952-08-22; 01-11; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:00; Brown, George; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lacasse, Fred; Link, Sam; Martin, John
  - Oh Mary, 1952-08-22; 01-12; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lacasse, Fred
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Lac du Flambeau Reservation (Wis.); Ojibwa dance; Ojibwa Indians--Music
  - Deer Song, 1953-06; 01-13; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:34; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shalifoe, Thomas
    Baraga (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ojibwa dance; Ojibwa Indians--Music
  - Catholic Ojibwa Hymn, 1953-06; 01-14; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:31; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shalifoe, Thomas
    Fourth, fifth, and sixth verses of "Jesus Wegwisiian" (Jesus who art the Son). From an LP titled "Songs and Dance of Great Lakes Indians," Ethnic Folkways Library, 1956. In section titled "Algonquians." Liner notes contain extensive notes on songs and performers, and musical analysis.
    Baraga (Mich.); Catholic Church--Hymns; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Ojibwa Indians--Religion
  - War Rally Song, 1954; 01-15; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:24; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Shagonaby, Susan
    Harbor Springs (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Bear Dance, 1954; 01-16; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:56; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Cross Village (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa dance; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Eagle Dance, 1954; 01-17; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:38; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Maple Sugar Song, 1954; 01-18; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:53; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Cross Village (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Hoot Owl Song, 1954; 01-19; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:36; Kenosha, David; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Hoot Owl Song, 1954-07-02; 01-20; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:01; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Mikado (Mich.); Ottawa Indians--Music
  - Coon Song, 1954-07-02; 01-21; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:48; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Rabbit Song, 1954-07-02; 01-22; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:41; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Canoe Song, 1954-07-02; 01-23; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:11; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Medicine Song, 1954-07-02; 01-24; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:57; Albert, Whitney; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
  - Grass Dance Song, 1953-08; 01-25; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:29; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Ojibwa dance; Ojibwa Indians--Music
  - Drinking Song, 1953-08; 01-26; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:09; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Thomas, Eli
    Drinking songs; Indians of North America--Michigan--Music; Isabella Reservation (Mich.); Ojibwa Indians--Music
  - Bear Dance Ritual, Circa 1954; 01-27; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:15; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Smoke, Percy
    From an LP titled "Songs and Dance of Great Lakes Indians," Ethnic Folkways Library, 1956. In section titled "Iroqouis -- Animal and War Dances." Liner notes contain extensive notes on songs and performers, and musical analysis.
    Nedrow (N.Y.); Onondaga dance; Onondaga Indians--Music
  - Eagle Dance Ritual, Circa 1954; 01-28; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:45; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Smoke, Percy
  - Wasase Rain Dance or War Dance, Circa 1954; 01-29; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:36; Buck, Richard; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    Cayuga dance; Cayuga Indians--Music; Six Nations Indian Reserve No. 40 (Ont.)
  - Scalp Dance, Circa 1954; 01-30; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:55; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lewis, Thomas
  - Corn Dance, Circa 1954; 01-31; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:06; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lewis, Thomas
    From an LP titled "Songs and Dance of Great Lakes Indians," Ethnic Folkways Library, 1956. In section titled "Food Spirit Dances." Liner notes contain extensive notes on songs and performers, and musical analysis.
  - Women's Dance (Four, old) (One, new), Circa 1954; 01-32; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:27; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Miller, Huron
    Onondaga dance; Onondaga Indians--Music; Six Nations Indian Reserve No. 40 (Ont.)
  - Fishing Dance and transition to Stomp Dance, Circa 1954; 01-33; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:38; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Miller, Huron
    Onondaga dance; Onondaga Indians--Music; Six Nations Indian Reserve No. 40 (Ont.); Stomp dance
  - Stomp Dance, Circa 1954; 01-34; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:19; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Miller, Huron
  - Two Future Prospects, Circa 1954; 01-35; 1.0 .mp3; 00:00:47; Buck, Gordie; Buck, Morris; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch
    From an LP titled "Songs and Dance of Great Lakes Indians," Ethnic Folkways Library, 1956. In section titled "Future Prospects." Liner notes contain extensive notes on songs and performers, and musical analysis.
    Cayuga Indians--Music; Six Nations Indian Reserve No. 40 (Ont.)
  - Seneca and Ojibwe Wesleyan Hymn, 1954-09; 01-36; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:10; Kurath, Gertrude Prokosch; Lyons, Mrs.; Pamptopee, Betty
    Hymns; Michigan; Ojibwa Indians--Music; Seneca Indians--Music